<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Learning Normal Asymmetry Representations for Homologous Brain Structures</title>
				<funder ref="#_zVM9WNh #_mwFRFqC #_v5AWJxz #_ndsGRKH">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Springer Nature Switzerland</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Springer Nature Switzerland</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Duilio</forename><surname>Deangeli</surname></persName>
							<email>ddeangeli@pladema.exa.unicen.edu.ar</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">PLADEMA</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yatiris</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">UNICEN</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tandil, Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Emmanuel</forename><surname>Iarussi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Universidad Torcuato Di Tella</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CABA</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Juan</forename><forename type="middle">Pablo</forename><surname>Princich</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">ENyS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CONICET-HEC-UNAJ</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Florencio Varela</addrLine>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mariana</forename><surname>Bendersky</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Universidad Torcuato Di Tella</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CABA</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">ENyS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CONICET-HEC-UNAJ</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Florencio Varela</addrLine>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Normal Anatomy Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UBA</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<region>CABA</region>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ignacio</forename><surname>Larrabide</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">PLADEMA</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yatiris</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">UNICEN</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tandil, Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">José</forename><forename type="middle">Ignacio</forename><surname>Orlando</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">PLADEMA</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Yatiris</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">UNICEN</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tandil, Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">CONICET</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Buenos Aires</settlement>
									<country key="AR">Argentina</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Learning Normal Asymmetry Representations for Homologous Brain Structures</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0302-9743</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">1611-3349</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Springer Nature Switzerland</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="87"/>
							<date type="published" when="2023" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E24FF7D10FE3F21B6F59015BCE9AD5EE</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-031-43993-3_8</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-05-13T19:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Normal asymmetry</term>
					<term>Brain MRI</term>
					<term>Anomaly detection</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Although normal homologous brain structures are approximately symmetrical by definition, they also have shape differences due to e.g. natural ageing. On the other hand, neurodegenerative conditions induce their own changes in this asymmetry, making them more pronounced or altering their location. Identifying when these alterations are due to a pathological deterioration is still challenging. Current clinical tools rely either on subjective evaluations, basic volume measurements or disease-specific deep learning models. This paper introduces a novel method to learn normal asymmetry patterns in homologous brain structures based on anomaly detection and representation learning. Our framework uses a Siamese architecture to map 3D segmentations of left and right hemispherical sides of a brain structure to a normal asymmetry embedding space, learned using a support vector data description objective. Being trained using healthy samples only, it can quantify deviations-from-normal-asymmetry patterns in unseen samples by measuring the distance of their embeddings to the center of the learned normal space. We demonstrate in public and in-house sets that our method can accurately characterize normal asymmetries and detect pathological alterations due to Alzheimer's disease and hippocampal sclerosis, even though no diseased cases were accessed for training. Our source code is available at https://github.com/duiliod/DeepNORHA.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>(Sub)cortical brain structures are approximately symmetrical between the left and right hemispheres <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>. Although their appearance and size are similar, they usually present difficult-to-characterize morphometric differences that vary among healthy populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, e.g. due to natural ageing <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Moreover, it has been studied that some neurological conditions, including Alzheimer's disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref> (AD), schizophrenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, and epilepsy <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>, are associated to asymmetry of the hippocampus or the amygdala <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref>. In regular medical practice, radiologists detect pathological changes in asymmetry by manually inspecting the structure using brain MRIs <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. They rely on their own subjective experience and knowledge, which varies among observers and lacks reproducibility, or standard quantitative measurements, e.g. volume differences in segmentations <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>, which fail to capture morphological asymmetries beyond differences in size <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>. No tools automate quantifying normal asymmetry patterns beyond volume <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, e.g. to detect deviations caused by a neurodegenerative disease. Some deep learning tools approximate this goal in a binary classification setting to differentiate one particular condition from normal cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>. However, this form is heavily specialized to discern asymmetry alterations associated with one specific disease, requiring retraining for every new condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>.</p><p>This paper introduces a novel framework for learning NORmal Asymmetries of Homologous cerebral structures (deep NORAH) based on anomaly detection and representation learning. Unlike previous methods that train Siamese neural networks with volume descriptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, our model takes 3D segmentations of left and right components from MRIs as inputs, and maps them into an embedding that summarizes their shape differences. Essentially, our Siamese architecture includes a shape characterization encoder that extracts morphological features directly from segmentations and an Asymmetry Projection Head (APH) that merges their differences to create a compact representation of asymmetries. To ensure this embedding learns the heterogeneity in normal individuals, our network is trained only with healthy samples, using a self-supervised pre-training stage based on a Contractive Autoencoder (CAE) and then fine-tuning using a Support Vector Data Description (SVDD) objective. Our experiments in the hippocampus show that our model can easily project new cases to the normal asymmetry space. Furthermore, we show that the distance between the embedding and the center of the normal space is a measure of deviation-from-normalasymmetry, as we empirically observed increased distance in pathological cases. Hence, deep NORAH can be used to diagnose, e.g. AD, hippocampal sclerosis and even mild cognitive impairment (MCI) by simply detecting the differences in asymmetry regarding the normal set, without needing diseased cases for training.</p><p>In summary, our contributions are as follows: (i) ours is the first unsupervised deep learning model explicitly designed to learn normal asymmetries in homologous brain structures; (ii) although it is trained only with normal data, it can be used to detect diseased samples by quantifying the degree of deviation with respect to a healthy population , unlike existing methods that capture only disease-specific asymmetries <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>; and (iii) compared to other state-of-theart anomaly detection approaches, our method demonstrates consistently better results for discriminating both synthetic and diseased-related asymmetries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> depicts a flowchart of our method as applied in test time. Our goal is to automatically measure the asymmetry of a given homologous brain structure x = (x L , x R ), with x L and x R being the 3D segmentations of its left and right lateral elements, and learn if these differences are typical for a normal population. To do so, we propose to learn a Siamese deep neural network F θ (x) = z L-R with θ parameters using an anomaly detection objective and samples from healthy individuals. z L-R is a compact representation of the asymmetries in x, obtained by learning a hypersphere S with a center c and minimum radius. In test time, samples with normal asymmetries are projected to the vicinity of c, while those with unexpected differences fall far from this point. As a result, the distance d = F θ (x)c 2 2 can be used as a deviation-from-normal-asymmetry index. To train this model, we first learn a 3D shape encoder f θEN (x) as part of a CAE, using normal samples (Sect. 2.1). This network can take any single segmentation of a lateral element x (i) as input, and map it to a high dimensional shape representation h * (i) . We then add this encoder to a Siamese architecture by attaching it to an APH, which captures the differences in shape from h * L and h * R , and project them into the unique asymmetry embedding z L-R . To this end, both the pre-trained encoder and the APH are trained using a deep SVDD objective (Sect. 2.2). This second learning phase not only trains the APH from scratch but fine-tunes the shape encoder to capture those morphological characteristics that are the most common source of asymmetry in normal individuals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Pre-training the Shape Characterization Encoder as a CAE</head><p>Our shape encoder f θEN indistinctly map an arbitrarily left or right segmentation x (i) of an homologous structure x, to a feature vector h * (i) that describes its shape. To this end, we apply a warm-up learning phase that trains f θEN as the encoding path of a CAE, using a self-supervised learning loss (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>). Hence, the encoder is simultaneously trained with a decoder g θDE (i) using a reconstruction task. The encoder compresses the input into a lower-dimensional representation h * (i) by applying a series of convolutional and pooling operations, and the decoder tries to reconstruct it using upsampling operations and convolutions.</p><p>Formally, let (g θDE •f θEN )(x (i) ) be a convolutional CAE with a decoding path g θDE (h * (i) ) with parameters θ DE that outputs a reconstruction x(i) of the input x (i) from its hidden representation h * (i) . This is achieved by minimizing a mean square error objective (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>). After it, the decoder is discarded and the shape encoder is used in the Siamese setting of our anomaly detection network. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Learning Normal Asymmetries with a Siamese Network</head><p>Asymmetry Projection Head. The purpose of our APH is to project the shape representation h * obtained by f θEN into a compact embedding z L-R (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>) that better describes normal population asymmetry characteristics. In our implementation, this network is a multilayer perceptron (MLP) with two fully connected (FC) layers separated with a ReLU activation. The first FC layer is used in a Siamese setting by feeding it with the shape representations h * L and h * R of the left and right elements, respectively. Each of these inputs are projected into two new feature vectors h L and h R with a lower dimensionality. A merging operation (e.g. subtraction or concatenation) combines them into a joint representation h (L-R) , which is projected by the second FC layer into the asymmetry embedding z (L-R) . Notice that the main design choices to be made are the dimensionality of the outputs of each FC layer and the merging operation.</p><p>One-Class Deep SVDD. In order to enforce z (L-R) to represent the asymmetry characteristics of normal individuals, we train the Siamese architecture F θ (x) in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref> using an anomaly detection objective. We adopted the one-class deep SVDD approach proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, which solves:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">min θ 1 n n i=1 F θ (x (i) ) -c 2 + λ 2 θ 2 2 . (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">)</formula><p>The first term in Eq. 1 is a quadratic loss that penalizes the Euclidean distance of z (L-R) from the center c of a hypersphere S, that is implicitly determined by the distance itself in the representation space. The second term is a classic weight decay regularizer, controlled by λ. Notice that we do not contract S by explicitly penalizing its radius and samples lying outside its boundary, but by minimizing their mean Euclidean distance with respect to c <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>. To avoid convergence to a collapsed trivial solution with all zero weights, all layers in F θ do not use bias terms <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>, and the center c was set to the average z (L-R) obtained by feeding F θ with all training samples before fine-tuning, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>. At that stage, f is already pre-trained using the self-supervised strategy described in Sect. 2.1, but the APH has random weights. Nevertheless, we experimentally observed that this center c is already enough to avoid a collapsed S.</p><p>Deviation-from-Normal-Asymmetry Index. The distance between the asymmetry embedding of an unseen sample x and the center of the learned hypersphere, s(x; c) = F θ (x)c 2 , can be used as a deviation-from-normalasymmetry index: when the input x is a normal sample, its asymmetry embedding is expected to lie in the vicinity of c, then associated to a small s value; on the other hand, if x is the segmentation of a subject with abnormal asymmetries, its associated z (L-R) will lie afar from c, reporting a higher s value.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Experimental Setup</head><p>We studied our method for hippocampal asymmetry characterization as a use case. First, we tested its ability to capture deviations in asymmetry using synthetically altered hippocampi with increased deformations, in a controlled setting. Then, we indirectly evaluated its performance as a diagnostic tool for neurodegenerative conditions, using s as a deviation-from-normal-asymmetry index.</p><p>Finally, we performed an ablation study to understand the influence of design factors such as the shape encoder architecture, APH size, and merging operation.</p><p>Materials. We used a total of 3243 3D T1 brain MRIs, including 2945 from normal control (NC) individuals, 71 from patients with MCI, 179 with AD, and 16 and 32 with right (HSR) and left (HSL) hippocampal sclerosis, respectively. Samples were retrospectively collected from OASIS <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> (NC = 2217, AD = 33), IXI <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> (NC = 539) and ADNI <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> (NC = 53, AD = 33, MCI = 71) public sets, and from two in-house databases, ROFFO (NC = 83) and HEC (NC = 53, HSL = 32, HSR = 16), (see supp. mat. for demographics characteristics). All images were integrated in a single set, that we split into training, validation and test.</p><p>The training set was used to learn patterns of normal asymmetry, with NC from ROFFO (63), IXI (539), and 70% of the NC from OASIS. Ages ranged from 19 to 95 years old, to ensure capturing normal variations due to natural aging. 60 NC images were kept aside for validation (see below). The test sets, were used to evaluate the diagnostic ability of our method on different cohorts. TEST-ADNI and TEST-HEC sets include all subjects from ADNI and HEC sets, while TEST-OASIS includes all AD and the remaining 30% of NC from OASIS. Images from different devices were aligned and normalized to a standard reference MNI T1 template using SPM12 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>. Hippocampal segmentations were obtained using HippMapp3r <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, a CNN model that is robust to atrophies and lesions. The resulting segmentations were cropped to create separate masks for each hippocampus, each with size 64 × 64 × 64 voxels. We created synthetic validation sets with abnormal hippocampal asymmetries to study the model's ability to identify asymmetries of different variations. We used 60 normal hippocampal segmentations (20 from ROFFO and 40 from OASIS) and applied elastic deformations <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref> with σ ∈ {3, 5, 8} to one of the two hippocampi of 20 individuals, resulting in 60 simulated abnormal pairs (see supp. mat. for qualitative examples). Four validation sets S σ were created, with σ = 3, 5, 8 and all, including the original 60 normal pairs and the corresponding simulated cases in the first three and a mix of all of them in the last one. This allowed us to perform hyperparameter tuning and evaluate the model's performance. Implementation Details. We studied two backbones for our Siamese shape encoder: a LeNet-based architecture similar to the one in <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> (but adapted to 3D inputs), with 3 convolutional layers with 16, 32 and 64 5 × 5 × 5 filters, each followed by a 3D batch normalization (BN) layer and a ReLU operation; and a deeper CNN equal to the encoding path of the CAE in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> to learn anatomical shape variations from 3D organs. The size of the FC layers in the APH were adjusted based on the validation set. For CAE pre-training, the LeNet based encoder was attached to a bottleneck FC layer, followed by a symmetric decoder with 3 trilinear interpolation upsamplings, each followed by a convolutional layer with 3D BN and ReLU. For the deeper encoder, on the other hand, we used the exact same CAE from <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Further details about the architectures are provided in the supp. mat. We pre-trained the networks using the CAE approach for 250 epochs, and then fine-tuned them with SVDD for another 250 epochs. In all cases, we used Adam optimization with a learning rate of 10 -4 , weight decay regularization with a factor of 10 -6 and a batch size of 12 hippocampi pairs. We used PyTorch 1.12 and SciKit Learn for our experiments.</p><p>Baselines. We compared our model with respect to other multiple approaches. To account for the standard clinical methods, we included the absolute and normalized volume differences (AVD and NVD, respectively), used in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> as scores for asymmetry. We also included shallow one-class support vector machines (OC-SVMs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> trained with the same NC subjects than ours but different feature sets. We used ShapeDNA <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> (ShapeDNA + OC-SVM), which was previously studied to characterize hippocampal asymmetries <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>, and a combined large feature vector (LFV + OC-SVM) including volumetric differences, ShapeDNA and shape features obtained using PyRadiomics (sphericity, compactness, quadratic compactness, elongation, flatness, spherical disproportion, surface volume ratio, maximum 2D diameter, maximum 3D diameter and Major Axis). For standard deep practices in anomaly detection, we trained hybrid CAE + shallow OC-SVM using our LeNet (LeNet-CAE + OC-SVM) and deeper backbones (Oktay et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> + OC-SVM). Finally, a binary network was trained to detect AD cases (AD classification), in order to have a supervised counterpart for comparison. We used a larger training set that, apart from the same NC subjects used for the anomaly detection models, included all samples in TEST-OASIS. The validation set had in this case the remaining NCs from OASIS and AD cases from ADNI.</p><p>The same backbone architecture was used, but with an additional FC layer that had softmax activation for classification, as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Results and Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Characterization of Normal and Disease Related Asymmetries</head><p>To test our hypothesis that samples with abnormal hippocampal asymmetries deviate from the center of the normal hypersphere, we evaluated the distances s(x; c) between all samples in the validation and test sets and grouped them by disease category. The distribution of these distances is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> (left), with statistical significance assessed using Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon rank-sum tests (α = 0.05) with Bonferroni correction applied for multiple comparisons. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> (right) represent the t-SNE projection of all representations. NC subjects are closely grouped in this plot, with the smallest distances to the center among all groups. These values are significantly lower than those obtained for synthetically altered samples (p &lt; 0.004) and individuals with MCI (p &lt; 0.017), AD (p &lt; 0.0083), HSL (p &lt; 0.017) and HSR (p &lt; 0.017). Distances increase proportionally to σ for synthetic cases and conditions with unilateral hippocampus shrinkage such as HSL and HSR, which are located at the extremes in the t-SNE representation. Synthetic cases with σ = 8 group around one of the clusters, while those with σ = 5 and 3 are scattered closer but still far from the center. MCI subjects from ADNI are scattered similarly to NC samples from OASIS, which is consistent with their distances. This could be due to cognitive decline in MCI cases not necessarily associated with alterations in hippocampal asymmetry, which can resemble that of NC, but rather with changes in other brain areas such as amygdala or thalamus <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>. It is possible then that the MCI subjects in this study do not exhibit hippocampal asymmetry changes large enough to be distinguished from those in healthy controls. AD cases, on the other hand, are seen far from the hypersphere center as well, reporting distances higher than those from NC. Finally, when compared one another, we observed significant differences in the distances between NC from ADNI set (p &lt; 0.0055), but not between OASIS and HEC sets (p &lt; 0.1241).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Comparison with Other Approaches</head><p>The evaluation results of different methods are displayed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>. Volumetric based approaches only detected unilateral atrophies in synthetic and HSL/R cases and poor performance for MCI and AD. Feature-based methods performed slightly better for AD and synthetic but dropped for HSL/R and MCI, lacking the required robustness to abnormal asymmetry changes. Hybrid CAE + OC-SVM models had good performance on synthetic data but not on real data tasks. Finally, the AD binary classifier was only able to detect AD but failed in any other cases, which is consistent with the disease specialization hypothesis. Our method, on the contrary, outperformed all other methods for detecting both synthetically induced and pathological changes in hippocampal asymmetry. Notice,  1.00 (1.00-1.00) 1.00 (1.00-1.00) Deep NORAH (with CAE pretr.) 0.99 (0.99-1.00) 0.93 (0.87-0.97) 1.00 (0.99-1.00) 0.92 (0.86-0.96) 1.00 (1.00-1.00) 1.00 (1.00-1.00) however, that the AD classification method is not a state-of-the-art approach but a comparable model with approximately the same backbone than ours. Other alternatives such as <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref> might achieve much higher AUC values.</p><p>Ablation Analysis. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> includes results with and without our CAE pretraining. This stage significantly improve performance in synthetic, MCI and AD (OASIS) cases, perhaps due to a better estimate of c. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> illustrates the variations in AUC in S σ=all when changing the merge operation and the size of h(•). Using differences seems to be much more efficient in terms of capacity usage, with almost the same AUC obtained without a FC layer for dimensionality reduction (0.977) and with a FC layer with 512 outputs (0.997). Nevertheless, when applied on real cases, adding this additional component aids to improve the discrimination performance (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>). Finally, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> shows results in S σ=all for different encoder settings. Using a Siamese approach with difference as merge operation was in all cases superior than the other alternatives. In terms of architecture, LeNet and deep backbones showed similar performance, with LeNet being slightly better. This might be due to a higher number of FC parameters, as the output of the shape encoder is a vector with &gt;32k features.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusions</head><p>We presented a novel anomaly detection-based method for automatically characterizing normal asymmetry in homologous brain structures. Supervised alternatives restrict the definition of normal individuals due to explicitly learning their differences with respect to subjects with a specific condition. This implies that they ignore the asymmetry in control subjects, capturing only the asymmetries induced by the analyzed disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, and requiring retraining to detect new conditions unseen during training. Conversely, our unsupervised alternative leverages a recently introduced one-class-based objective to learn the space of normal asymmetries. Hence, it can detect diseased samples by quantifying their distance to the control space. Our experiments on hippocampus data showed that our approach could effectively use symmetry information to characterize normal populations and then identify disease presence by contrast, even though only NC subjects are used for training. Our model can potentially be applied to other homologous brain structures and diverse cohorts to aid radiologists in quantifying asymmetries of a normal brain better. In its current form, the model inherits the limitations of the segmentation approach, although it showed to achieve good performance using the outputs of HippMapp3r. Furthermore, it has the burden of not offering qualitative feedback, so future work should focus on bringing interpretability to this tool, e.g., by means of occlusion analysis.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Schematic of our framework for capturing abnormal asymmetries in homologous brain structures from 3D MRI.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,113,97,230,51,224,92,81,52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Training sequence of our method.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Evaluation of our approach for characterizing different asymmetry patterns. Left: Distribution of distances s(x; c) for each disease and NC group. Right: t-SNE representation of the normal asymmetry embeddings.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,88,80,53,87,249,04,82,12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig. 4. APH ablation.</figDesc><graphic coords="9,95,46,70,28,65,92,65,32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>AUC (95% CI) table for different approaches. (0.62-0.81) 0.56 (0.46-0.66) 0.55 (0.42-0.67) 0.62 (0.51-0.74) 0.95 (0.89-0.99) 0.94 (0.82-1.00) NVD 0.82 (0.74-0.89) 0.58 (0.48-0.68) 0.62 (0.49-0.74) 0.64 (0.53-0.74) 0.95 (0.88-1.00) 0.94 (0.83-1.00)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Method</cell><cell>Synthetic</cell><cell>MCI</cell><cell cols="2">AD (ADNI) AD (OASIS) HSL</cell><cell>HSR</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">AVD 0.72 ShapeDNA + OC-SVM 0.66 (0.56-0.74) 0.52 (0.42-0.60) 0.66 (0.55-0.76) 0.47 (0.35-0.60)</cell><cell cols="2">0.80 (0.69-0.90) 0.90 (0.81-0.98)</cell></row><row><cell>LFV + OC-SVM</cell><cell cols="3">0.93 (0.89-0.97) 0.58 (0.49-0.66) 0.67 (0.57-0.76) 0.65 (0.53-0.77)</cell><cell cols="2">0.92 (0.88-0.96) 0.98 (0.95-1.00)</cell></row><row><cell>LeNet-CAE + OC-SVM</cell><cell cols="3">0.95 (0.91-0.98) 0.48 (0.38-0.58) 0.50 (0.37-0.61) 0.46 (0.40-0.51)</cell><cell cols="2">0.77 (0.67-0.86) 0.69 (0.56-0.81)</cell></row><row><cell>Oktay et al. + OC-SVM</cell><cell cols="3">0.94 (0.90-0.98) 0.45 (0.35-0.56) 0.48 (0.35-0.59) 0.47 (0.42-0.53)</cell><cell cols="2">0.80 (0.69-0.88) 0.76 (0.65-0.86)</cell></row><row><cell>AD classification</cell><cell cols="5">0.49 (0.47-0.50) 0.64 (0.56-0.70) 0.73 (0.63-0.83) (Used for training) 0.52 (0.48-0.56) 0.54 (0.48-0.61)</cell></row><row><cell>Deep NORAH (w/o CAE pretr.)</cell><cell cols="3">0.79 (0.71-0.87) 0.59 (0.48-0.69) 0.99 (0.99-1.00) 0.76 (0.67-0.84)</cell><cell cols="2">1.00 (0.99-1.00) 1.00 (0.99-1.00)</cell></row><row><cell>Deep NORAH (</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>w/o FC dim. red.) 0</head><label></label><figDesc>.98 (0.94-1.00) 0.70 (0.60-0.79) 0.76 (0.65-0.87) 0.65 (0.54-0.76)</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Shape encoder ablation.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Backbone</cell><cell cols="3">Siamese Sagittal flip Merge</cell><cell>Num.</cell><cell>AUC</cell></row><row><cell>architec-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>operation</cell><cell>params</cell><cell>(Sσ=all)</cell></row><row><cell>ture</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LeNet</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>5.4M</cell><cell>0.62</cell></row><row><cell>LeNet</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>Concat</cell><cell>2.7M</cell><cell>0.71</cell></row><row><cell>LeNet</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>Diff</cell><cell>2.7M</cell><cell>0.76</cell></row><row><cell>LeNet</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>Concat</cell><cell>2.7M</cell><cell>0.73</cell></row><row><cell>LeNet</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>Diff</cell><cell>2.7M</cell><cell>0.95</cell></row><row><cell>Deeper</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>N/A</cell><cell>1.1M</cell><cell>0.58</cell></row><row><cell>Deeper</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>Concat</cell><cell>555K</cell><cell>0.72</cell></row><row><cell>Deeper</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✗</cell><cell>Diff</cell><cell>555K</cell><cell>0.81</cell></row><row><cell>Deeper</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>Concat</cell><cell>555K</cell><cell>0.75</cell></row><row><cell>Deeper</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>✓</cell><cell>Diff</cell><cell>555K</cell><cell>0.94</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments. This study was funded by <rs type="grantNumber">PIP GI 2021-2023 0102472</rs> (<rs type="affiliation">CON-ICET</rs>) and PICTs <rs type="grantNumber">2019-00070</rs>, <rs type="grantNumber">2020-00045</rs> and <rs type="grantNumber">2021-00023</rs> (<rs type="affiliation">Agencia I+D+i</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_zVM9WNh">
					<idno type="grant-number">PIP GI 2021-2023 0102472</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_mwFRFqC">
					<idno type="grant-number">2019-00070</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_v5AWJxz">
					<idno type="grant-number">2020-00045</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_ndsGRKH">
					<idno type="grant-number">2021-00023</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Information</head><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-43993-3 8.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Alzheimer&apos;s disease neuroimaging initiative</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Adni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://adni.loni.usc.edu/Acce-ssedFeb" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2023</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="http://brain-development.org/ixidataset" />
		<title level="m">IXI dataset website</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-09">Feb. 9 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexual dimorphism and hemispheric asymmetry of hippocampal volumetric integrity in normal aging and Alzheimer disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ardekani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Neuroradiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesial temporal damage in temporal lobe epilepsy: a volumetric MRI study of the hippocampus, amygdala and parahippocampal region</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bernasconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="469" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Artificial intelligence for diagnosis and prognosis in neuroimaging for dementia; a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Borchert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">medRxiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2021" to="2033" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abnormalities of thalamic volume and shape in schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Csernansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="896" to="902" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altered neuroanatomical asymmetries of subcortical structures in subjective cognitive decline, amnestic mild cognitive impairment, and alzheimer&apos;s disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alzheimers Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1121" to="1132" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hippocampal Segmentation for Brains with Extensive Atrophy Using Three-dimensional Convolutional Neural Networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goubran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>Wiley Online Library</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. rep</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain asymmetries in autism and developmental language disorder: a nested whole-brain analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Herbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="226" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain asymmetry detection and machine learning classification for diagnosis of early dementia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Magoulas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sensors</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">778</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hippocampal shape and asymmetry analysis by cascaded convolutional neural networks for Alzheimer&apos;s disease diagnosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Elahifasaee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11682-020-00427-y</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11682-020-00427-y" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Imag. Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2330" to="2339" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using deep Siamese neural networks for detection of brain asymmetries associated with Alzheimer&apos;s disease and mild cognitive impairment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magn. Reson. Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="190" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetrical atrophy of thalamic Subnuclei in Alzheimer&apos;s disease and amyloid-positive mild cognitive impairment is associated with key clinical features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assess. Disease Monit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="690" to="699" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Alzheimer&apos;s Dementia: Diagnosis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open access series of imaging studies: longitudinal MRI data in nondemented and demented older adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cogn. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2677" to="2684" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomically constrained neural networks (ACNNS): application to cardiac image enhancement and segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Oktay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Trans. Med. Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="395" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining multivariate normative rules for healthy aging using neuroimaging and machine learning: an application to Alzheimer&apos;s disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Alzheimers Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Topographic divergence of atypical cortical asymmetry and atrophy patterns in temporal lobe epilepsy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">145</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1285" to="1298" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetry of the hippocampus and amygdala in MRI volumetric measurements of normal adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pedraza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bowers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gilmore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JINS</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="678" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistical parametric mapping: the analysis of functional brain images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Penny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic performance of MRI volumetry in epilepsy patients with hippocampal sclerosis supported through a random forest automatic classification algorithm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Princich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">613967</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased hippocampal shape asymmetry and volumetric ventricular asymmetry in autism spectrum disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage: Clin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deep one-class classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PMLR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4393" to="4402" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>ICML</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Support vector method for novelty detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Neural. Inform. Process. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tortora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Derrickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles of anatomy and physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Van Tulder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">elasticdeform: Elastic deformations for n-dimensional images</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Whole-brain analysis reveals increased neuroanatomical asymmetries in dementia for hippocampus and amygdala</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wachinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3253" to="3266" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomical and functional correlates of human hippocampal volume asymmetry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Woolard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heckers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psych. Res.: Neuroimag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="48" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anomaly detection using improved deep SVDD model with data structure preservation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Deng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recogn. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
