<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Physics-Informed Conditional Autoencoder Approach for Robust Metabolic CEST MRI at 7T</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Springer Nature Switzerland</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Springer Nature Switzerland</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Junaid</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rajput</surname></persName>
							<email>junaid.rajput@fau.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pattern Recognition Lab Friedrich</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Alexander-University Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tim</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Möhle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Moritz</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fabian</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Angelika</forename><surname>Mennecke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jochen</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sembill</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joji</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kuramatsu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Manuel</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Arnd</forename><surname>Dörfler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pattern Recognition Lab Friedrich</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Alexander-University Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Moritz</forename><surname>Zaiss</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Erlangen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Physics-Informed Conditional Autoencoder Approach for Robust Metabolic CEST MRI at 7T</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0302-9743</idno>
						<idno type="eISSN">1611-3349</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Springer Nature Switzerland</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="449" to="458"/>
							<date type="published" when="2023" />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F424F5FAE187BD5793A76A6232ABC061</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/978-3-031-43993-3_44</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-05-13T19:28+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Physics-informed autoencoder</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Chemical exchange saturation transfer (CEST) is an MRI method that provides insights on the metabolic level. Several metabolite effects appear in the CEST spectrum. These effects are isolated by Lorentzian curve fitting. The separation of CEST effects suffers from the inhomogeneity of the saturation field B1. This leads to inhomogeneities in the associated metabolic maps. Current B1 correction methods require at least two sets of CEST-spectra. This at least doubles the acquisition time. In this study, we investigated the use of an unsupervised physics-informed conditional autoencoder (PICAE) to efficiently correct B1 inhomogeneity and isolate metabolic maps while using a single CEST scan. The proposed approach integrates conventional Lorentzian model into the conditional autoencoder and performs voxel-wise B1 correction and Lorentzian line fitting. The method provides clear interpretation of each step and is inherently generative. Thus, CEST-spectra and fitted metabolic maps can be created at arbitrary B1 levels. This is important because the B1 dispersion contains information about the exchange rates and concentration of metabolite protons, paving the way for their quantification. The isolated maps for tumor data showed a robust B1 correction and more than 25% increase in structural similarity index (SSIM) with gadolinium reference image compared to the standard interpolation-based method and subsequent Lorentzian curve fitting. This efficient correction method directly results in at least 50% reduction in scan time.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Chemical exchange saturation transfer (CEST) is a novel metabolic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) method that allows to detect molecules in tissue based on chemical exchange of their mobile protons with water protons <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>. CEST works by selectively saturating the magnetization of a specific pool of protons, such as those in metabolites or proteins, by applying narrow-band radiofrequency (RF) pulses at their respective Larmor frequency. Due to chemical exchange this saturation state is transferred to the water pool and a decrease in the detected water signal provides information about the concentration and exchange rate of the underlying molecules. This procedure is repeated for several RF frequencies to acquire the so-called CEST-spectrum in each voxel. CEST-MRI offers several promising contrasts that correlate with the diagnosis of diseases such as ischemic stroke <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, brain tumors <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and neurodegenerative diseases <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>. The CESTspectrum contains effects of proton pools of various chemical components in the tissue, typically isolated by a Lorentzian model <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> that is derived form the underlying physics of the Bloch-McConnell equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. In this conventional method, several Lorentzian distributions are fitted to the CEST-spectrum using nonlinear least squares method <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, and the amplitude of each fitted distribution represents a particular metabolic map. The number of Lorentzian functions utilized in this process depends on the expected number of exchanging proton pools present in the spectrum. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref> shows an example of an acquired CEST-spectrum and the corresponding 5-pool Lorentzian fit. Increasing the static magnetic field B 0 (e.g., with B 0 = 7T), enhances spectral resolution, but leads to significant variations in the B 1 amplitude of the saturating RF field across the field of view (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>). This B 1 inhomogeneity is corrected by acquiring CEST-spectra at various RF field strengths (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>) and then interpolating between them at fixed B 1 to produce the B 1 -robust metabolic CEST contrast maps <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. This B 1 correction increases the acquisition time at least twofold.</p><p>Hunger et al. shown that supervised learning can be used to generate B 1robust CEST maps, coining the DeepCEST approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>. However, the previous work on generating the B 1 -robust CEST contrasts rely on valid target data and the underlying assumptions to generate it, and can only create CEST maps at one particular B 1 level.</p><p>In this work, we developed a conditional autoencoder (CAE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> to generate B 1 -homogeneous CEST-spectra at arbitrary B 1 levels, and a physics-informed autoencoder (PIAE) to fit the 5-pool Lorentzian model to the B 1 corrected CEST-spectra. This inclusion of physical knowledge in the form of known operators in neural nets (NN) is expected to reduce the absolute error margin of the model <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref> and to increase its interpretability. Both CAE and PIAE are trained in an unsupervised end-to-end method that eliminates the shortcomings of conventional Lorentzian curve fitting and produces robust CEST contrast at arbitrary B 1 levels without the need for an additional acquisition scan. We called the proposed method physics-informed conditional autoencoder (PICAE).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p>Data Measurements. CEST imaging was performed in seven subjects, including two glioblastoma patients, after written informed consent was obtained to investigate the dependence of CEST effects on B 1 in brain tissue. The local ethics committee approved the study. All volunteers were measured at three B 1 field strengths 0.72 μT, 1.0 μT, and 1.5 μT. A method as described by Mennecke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> was used to acquire CEST data on a 7T whole-body MRI system (MAGNE-TOM Terra, Siemens Healthcare GmbH, Erlangen, Germany). Saturated images were obtained for 54 non-equidistant frequency offsets ranging from -100 ppm to +100 ppm. The acquisition time per B 1 level was 6:42 min. The acquisition of the B 1 map required an additional 1:06 min.</p><p>Conditional Autoencoder. We developed a conditional autoencoder (CAE) to solve the B 1 inhomogeneity problem, which is essential for the generation of metabolic CEST contrast maps at 7T. The left part of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> describes the CAE. The encoding network of CAE took the raw CEST-spectrum and the corresponding effective B 1 value as input and generate a latent space that was concatenated once with the same B 1 input value and passed to the decoder that reconstruct the uncorrected B 1 CEST-spectrum, and another time the latent space was concatenated with the desired/specific effective B 1 value to reconstruct the CEST-spectrum at a specific B 1 saturation amplitude. Both decoders shared the weights (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). For the development of the CAE networks, we used the well-known fully concatenated (FC) layers with leaky ReLU activations except for the last layer of decoder, which had a linear activation. The encoder and decoder both consisted of 4 layers, where the layers of the encoder successively contain 128, 128, 64, 32 neurons, while the layers of the decoder successively contain 32, 64, 128, 128 neurons. The input, latent space and output layers had 55, 17 and 54 neurons respectively.</p><p>Physics-Informed Autoencoder. The Lorentzian model and its B 1dispersion can be derived from the underlying spin physics described by the Bloch-McConnell equation system <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. The physics-informed autoencoder (PIAE) utilized fully connected NN as encoder and Lorentzian distribution generator as a decoder to perform the pixel-wise 5-pool Lorentzian curve fit to the CEST-spectrum (water, amide, amine, NOE, MT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The 5-pool model was described as</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Z(Δω) = 1 -L DS -L ssM T -L amine -L rN OE -L amide ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p>where L denotes the Lorentz function. The direct saturation pool (water) was defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">L DS = A DS 1 + ( Δω-δDS τDS /2 ) 2 .</formula><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">)<label>2</label></formula><p>The remaining other four pools were defined as</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">L i = A i 1 + ( Δω-δDS -δi τi/2</formula><p>) 2 , i ∈ amide, amine, rN OE, ssM T .</p><p>(</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">)<label>3</label></formula><p>The right part of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> describes the PIAE. The encoder of PIAE mapped the CEST-spectrum to the amplitudes A i , the full width half maximum (FWHM) τ i , and the water peak position δ DS of the 5-pool Lorentzian model. Its encoder consisted of four FC layers, each with 128 neurons with leaky ReLU activations. It had three so-called FC latent space layers with linear activation for position and exponential activations for FWHM and amplitudes of 5-pool Lorentzian model. The positions of amide, rNOE, ssMT, and amine were fixed at 3.5 ppm, -3.5 ppm, -3 ppm, and 2 ppm, respectively, and shifted with respect to the predicted position of the water peak. The decoder of PIAE consisted of a Lorentzian distribution generator (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). It generated samples of the 5-pool distributions exactly at the offsets Δω (i.e. between -100 ppm and 100 ppm) where the input CEST-spectrum was sampled, and combined them according to Eq. 1 to generate the input CEST spectrum with or without B 0 correction.</p><p>Bound Loss. The peak positions δ i and widths τ i of the pools had to be within certain bounds so that certain neurons in the latent space layer of PIAE would not be exchanged and provide the same pool parameters for all samples. We developed a simple cost function along the lines of the hinge loss <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, called the bound loss. Mathematically, it is defined as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">bound loss = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ abs(y -lb), if y &lt; lb abs(y -ub), if y &gt; ub 0, if y &lt;= ub AND y &gt;= lb ⎫ ⎬ ⎭ . (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">)</formula><p>The bound loss increases linearly as the output of the latent space neurons of PIAE exceeds or recede from the boundaries. The lower and upper limits for positions and widths are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> of the supplementary material.</p><p>Training and Evaluation. Four healthy volunteers formed the training and validation sets. The test set consisted of the two tumor patients and one healthy subject. To ensure that the outcomes were exclusively based on the CEST-spectrum and not influenced by spatial position, the training was carried out voxel-by-voxel. Consequently, there were approximately one million CESTspectra for the training process. CAE was first trained with MSE loss. In this step, the CAE encoder was fed with the CEST-spectrum of a specific B 1 saturation amplitude, and it generated two CEST-spectra, one for the input B 1 saturation level and the other for the B 1 level injected into the latent space (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). Later, it was trained with a combination of MSE loss and perception loss (MSE loss between the latent space of the CEST-spectra at two different B 1 levels). To incorporate perception loss, we used two forward passes with two different B 1 CEST-spectra and used perception loss to generate a latent space that is independent of B 1 saturation amplitude. The following equation describes the loss of the second step.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">CAE loss = MSE loss + 0.1 • perceptionloss (5)</formula><p>PIAE, on the other hand, was trained with a combination of MSE loss and bound loss. The PIAE loss was described as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">P IAE loss = MSE loss + bound loss,<label>(6)</label></formula><p>for evaluation we input the uncorrected CEST-spectrum acquired at 1μT and generated corrected CEST-spectra at B 1 0.5, 0.72, 1.0, 1.3, 1.5 μT. PIAE encoder yielded the amplitudes of 5-pool for B 1 corrected CEST-spectrum. Its decoder reconstructed the B 1 B 0 fitted CEST-spectrum. The B 0 correction simply refers to the shift of the position of the water peak to 0 ppm.</p><p>CEST Quantification. The multi-B 1 CEST-spectra allow quantification of CEST effects (amide, rNOE, amine) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> down to the exchange rate and concentration. The amplitudes of the CEST contrasts were expressed according to the definition in <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> as follows</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">A i = f i k i Z1 w 2 1 k i (k i + r 2i ) Z2 +w 2 1 α Z ref i ∈ amide, amine, rN OE, (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">)</formula><p>where f i , k i , and r 2i express the concentrations, exchange rates, and relaxation rates of the pools. Z ref defines the sum of all 5 distributions at the resonance frequency of the specific pool in B 1 B 0 corrected CEST-spectrum and w 1 is the frequency of the oscillating field.</p><p>The amplitudes of CEST contrasts in the Lorentzian function have the B 1 dispersion function given by the labeling efficiency α (Eq. 7). The exchange rate occurs here separately from the concentration, which allows their quantification via the B 1 dispersion. Concentration and exchange rate were fitted as a product and denoted as Z 1 (quantified maps), and k(k+r 2 ) was also fitted with the single term Z 2 using trust-region reflective least squares <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p>The comparison of PICAE with the conventional method <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> is shown in columns 1 and 2 of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>. The top image in column 3 shows the T 1 -weighted reference image enhanced with the exogenous contrast agent gadolinium (Gd-T 1 w), and the bottom image shows the B 1 -map. The tumor shows a typical so called gadolinium ring enhancement indicated by the arrow (a 15 ), which is also visible in the non-invasive and gadolinium-free CEST contrast maps (columns 1 and 2). The PICAE-CEST maps showed better visualization of this tumor feature compared to the conventional method. The proposed method yielded at least 25% increase in the structural similarity index (SSIM) with the Gd-T 1 w image for the ring enhancement region. The contrast maps also appear less noisy and more homogeneous over the whole brain compared to the Lorentzian fit on the interpolated-corrected B 1 CEST-spectra <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. To further evaluate the performance of PIAE and CAE, we b1-corrected the data using CAE and fitted it with the least squares method (CAE-Lorentzian fit). The comparison of the CEST maps produced by the conventional Lorentzian fit, the CAE-Lorentzian fit, and PICAE is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> using SSIM and gradient cross correlation (GCC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> for the Tumor ring region. Both the CAE-Lorentzian fit and PICAE were better than the conventional method. CAE-Lorentzian fit even outperformed PICAE for rNOE metabolic map and has similar performance for amide, but it has much lower performance for amine. The ability of PICAE to produce B 1 -robust CEST maps at arbitrary levels is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>, where different B 1 levels reveal different features of the heterogenous tumor. Quantification of chemical exchange rates and concentration, i.e., Z 1 = f•k, is shown in column 4. Z 1 (quantified maps) further improve the visualization of the ring enhancement area. Column 5 shows the Z 2 maps, which are combination of the exchange rate k and the relaxation rate r 2 . Quantified maps of amide, rNOE and amine for another tumor patient is shown in supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>. The accuracy of the CAE to generate particular B 1 CESTspectra is depicted using absolute error for acquisition at different B 1 levels (see supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). The performance was lower for B 1 0.72 μT, and 1.5 μT compared to 1 μT.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p>In this work, we analyzed the use of an autoencoder approach to generate B 1robust CEST contrast maps at arbitrary B 1 levels, which requires multiple acquisitions in conventional methods <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. The proposed method reduces the acquisition time by at least half when only two acquisitions are performed for B 1 correction. Supervised learning (DeepCEST) can generate CEST maps that are not susceptible to B 1 inhomogeneity at a particular B 1 , which already reduces acquisition time. However, DeepCEST was trained on data fitted using a conventional pipeline <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref> which has suboptimal B 1 correction (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>). Moreover, the different pools in the CEST spectrum are highlighted at different B 1 levels (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>). An approach that can generate a B 1 -robust CEST-spectrum at multiple B 1 levels allows quantifying the exchange rate and concentration of the CEST pools <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. The optimal B 1 can often only be selected at post-processing during the analysis of clinical data, as some clinically important features appear better at certain B 1 levels (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>). The proposed PICAE approach combines B 1 correction and Lorentzian curve fitting in a single step. The B 1 correction  was performed with a CAE, while the Lorentzian line fitting was performed with a PIAE using NN as the encoder and Lorentzian distribution generator as the decoder. This allows interpretation of the model while overcoming the drawback of curve fitting, such as being prone to noise (cf. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</p><p>The bound loss ensured that the positions of the pools were not interchanged. Quantification was still performed using the nonlinear least squares fit according to Eq. 7. The main reason for this was that it does not affect the acquisition time and it is affected by the Z ref .</p><p>The training was performed voxel-wise to ensure that the results are based only on the CEST-spectrum. This also results in about 1 million CEST-spectra for the training. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> shows the superiority of PICAE over the standard method, and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> shows that the results produced by PICAE are authentic because the quantification column Z 1 matches the amplitude images and follows Eq. 7. CAE-Lorentzian fitting showed comparable performance for amide and rNOE maps, but significantly lower performance for amine because it was still fitted using the least squares method, which is susceptible to noise in the input and takes up to 5 min to evaluate, compared to PICAE, which takes only a few seconds. The 1 μT acquisition performs better than 0.72 μT and 1.5 μT because it was trained for both lower and higher B 1 values compared to the other two acquisitions. The robustness of method for cyclic consistency <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> is displayed in supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>, which also shows the interpretability of the method. The results of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> also show the generalization capability of PICAE as it was trained without the tumor data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>In this work, we propose a PICAE method for evaluating 7T-CEST MRI that accounts for B 1 inhomogeneity in the input and predicts homogeneous metabolic CEST contrasts at arbitrary B 1 levels. The proposed generative and interpretable method enables (i) a reduction of scan time by at least 50%, (ii) the generation of reliable 7T-CEST contrast maps robust to B 1 inhomogeneity at multiple B 1 levels, (iii) a clear physical interpretation of the B 1 correction of the CESTspectra and the fitting of the Lorentzian model to it, and (iv) the quantification of the CEST contrast maps.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. (a) CEST-spectrum and the corresponding 5-pool Lorentzian fit. (b) CESTspectrum dependence on B1 saturation amplitude. (c) The B1 inhomogeneity map at 7T.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,44,31,304,13,335,98,92,35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Overview of the proposed physics-informed conditional autoencoder for B1 inhomogeneity correction (left) and Lorentzian curve fitting (right).</figDesc><graphic coords="4,41,79,53,69,340,21,231,01" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Comparison of B1 corrected CEST maps for conventional and PICAE methods (Columns 1 and 2). The top image in column 3 shows a reference Gd-T1w image, while the bottom image shows the B1 map. SSIM are calculated with respected to the Gd image for tumor region.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,41,79,61,40,340,24,259,30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Fig.4. B1-robust CEST maps at 0.5, 0.72, and 1.0 µT (columns 1-3), quantified maps (column 4), and combination of exchange and relaxation rates (column 5). SSIM are calculated with respected to the Gd image for tumor region.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,43,80,398,36,336,97,150,85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Camparision of PICAE with conventional and CAE-Lorentzian fit. SSIM and GCC are calculated with respected to the Gd image for tumor region.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Fit method</cell><cell>amide</cell><cell>rNOE</cell><cell>amine</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">SSIM GCC SSIM GCC SSIM GCC</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Conventional Lorentzian fit 0.09 0.13 0.10 0.18 0.09 0.07</cell></row><row><cell>CAE-Lorentzian fit</cell><cell cols="2">0.11 0.14 0.18 0.3</cell><cell>0.10 0.18</cell></row><row><cell>PICAE</cell><cell cols="3">0.12 0.13 0.14 0.27 0.16 0.27</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Information</head><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-43993-3_44.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating pH in the extracellular tumor microenvironment using CEST MRI and other imaging methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Pagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Radiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical exchange saturation transfer magnetic resonance imaging and its main and potential applications in pre-clinical and clinical studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Quant. Imaging Med. Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1747" to="1766" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linear projection-based CEST parameter estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Glang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/nbm.4697</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/nbm.4697" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NMR Biomed</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deepcest 7 t: fast and homogeneous mapping of 7 t CEST MRI parameters and their uncertainty quantification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hunger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magn. Reson. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1543" to="1556" />
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chronic glutamate toxicity in neurodegenerative diseaseswhat is the evidence?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lewerenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Maher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">469</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Precision learning: Towards use of known operators in neural networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schebesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Syben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Würfl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Steidl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fahrig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">24th International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2018. 2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="183" to="188" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning with known operators reduces maximum error bounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Mach. Intell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="380" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reaction rates by nuclear magnetic resonance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcconnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="430" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">7 tricks for 7 t CEST: improving reproducibility of multi-pool evaluation provides insights into effects of age and early stage parkinson&apos;s disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mennecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NMR Biomed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4717</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computing a trust region step</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moré</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Siam J. Sci. Stat. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="553" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of simularity measures for use in 2d-3d medical image registration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Penney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Desmedt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L G</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hawkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer-Assisted Intervention</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are loss functions all the same?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rosasco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>De Vito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Caponnetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Piana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Verri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neural Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1063" to="1076" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning structured output representation using deep conditional generative models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NIPS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Correction of b1-inhomogeneities for relaxation-compensated CEST imaging at 7 t. NMR in Biomed</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Windschuh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="537" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theory of chemical exchange saturation transfer MRI in the context of different magnetic fields</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zaiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gochberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NMR Biomed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4789</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using the amide proton signals of intracellular proteins and peptides to detect PH effects in MRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Payen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Traystman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van Zijl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1085" to="1090" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unpaired image-to-image translation using cycle-consistent adversarial networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Isola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Efros</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">2017 IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2242" to="2251" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemical exchange saturation transfer (CEST): what is in a name and what isn&apos;t?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C M</forename><surname>Van Zijl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Yadav</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magn. Reson. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="927" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
